 
AMVER Report Formats	   
	Information	SP	PR	DR	FR	Remarks	   
Report Identifier (SP, PR, DR, or FP)	X	X	X	X		   
A	Vessel name	X	X	X	X		   
B	Time of report	X	X	X		Expressed in UTC as a 6-digit date-time group followed by the letters Z, GMT, or UTC and optionally by a 3-letter abbreviation for the month.	   
C	Position of vessel (latitude/longitude) at time of report		X	X		See Note 1.	   
E	Current course at time of report in degrees true	X	X	X		Expressed as a 3-digit number.	   
F	Vessel’s estimated average speed over the ground for the remainder of the voyage	X	X	X		Expressed as a 3-digit number representing knots and tenths of knots. See Note 2.	   
G	Port of departure by name and position	X				It is important to give the position of the port as the name alone does not always uniquely identify the port.	   
I	Vessel’s next port and ETA	X	R	C/R		See Note 3.	   
K	Vessels actual arrival at the destination				X		   
L	Route information	X		C		See Note 4.	   
M	Information on the best way to contact the vessel quickly in the event of a distress at sea.	O	O	O			   
V	Medical capability aboard the vessel	O				See Note 5.	   
X	Used for any English language amplifying comments or remarks the vessel may wish to send AMVER regarding its current voyage (e.g. change of vessel name, flag or owners etc.)	O	O	O	O		   
Y	Used to request relay of the AMVER report to certain other ship reporting systems	O	O	O	O	Currently includes MAREP, JASREP,
JUSSREP, and CHILREP.	   
Z	End of report	X	X	X	X	Must be the last line in every AMVER report as it is used by the AMVER computer to signal the end of the report.	   
KEY						   
X	Required information				   
O	Optional information				   
R	Recommended information				   
C	Required information if destination or route changes				   
Note 1.—Latitudes are always expressed as a 4-digit group followed by N (North) or S (South). The first two digits are interpreted as degrees; the second two digits are interpreted as minutes.
Longitudes are always expressed as a 5-digit group followed by E (East) or W (West). The first three digits are interpreted as degrees; the second two digits are interpreted as minutes.
It is important to use all digits every time, filling leading digit positions with zeroes as needed, to ensure accurate interpretation of position information.	   
Note 2.—This is a very important line to report as this speed is used for AMVER's dead reckoning computations unless a different speed is provided for a specific leg of a voyage (see L line). If no speed is given, AMVER will use an assumed speed. It is important to use all digits when specifying a speed to ensure accurate interpretation.	   
Note 3.—It is important to include the port's position as well as its name. The ETA at the next port is also important, especially when a U.S. port is the destination. In all cases, the ETA is compared with AMVER’s computed ETA as a check on the accuracy and consistency of all voyage route information. 	   
Note 4.—These lines are the most complex lines in an AMVER report but they are critical to the success of the AMVER system. Complete route information should be provided in all SPs and DRs. As many L lines as needed may be used to describe the vessel’s intended route. However, detailed route information caused by maneuvering over short distances near coasts should not be included. In these cases an approximate route using fewer turn points and the “COASTAL” navigation method should be provided. All L lines except the last one in the report require the navigation method to the next turn point, latitude and longitude of the next turn point, and the ETA at the next turn point. The final L line in an SP requires only the navigation method from the last turn point to the destination. Further amplifying instructions for the L line are, as follows:
1.	Navigation Method.—The navigation method is required on all L lines. It is the method used to get from the last specified position to the one specified in this L line. Three types of navigation methods recognized by AMVER, as follows:
a.	Rhumb Line (RL).
b.	Great Circle (GC).
c.	Coastal (COASTAL)—The “COASTAL” method should be used only to indicate when an approximate route near a coast is used in place of the many turn points required to describe the vessel’s true track. However, enough turn points should be provided to keep AMVER’s plot of the vessel’s position within 25 miles of the vessel’s true position. The “COASTAL” method should never be used for major portions of a route.
2.	Leg Speed.—The leg speed is an optional item on L lines. It is the anticipated average speed over the ground on the leg which ends at the position given in the same L line. Leg speed should be used whenever the anticipated average speed on a leg is significantly different from the anticipated average speed for the voyage as reported in the F line. As a general rule, a difference of 1 knot or more should be considered significant.
3.	Latitude.—This is the latitude of the next turn point. It is required in all L lines except the last one in the report.
4.	Longitude.—This is the longitude of the next turn point. It is required in all L lines except the last one in the report. The final position in a route is assumed to be the port of destination.
5.	Port or landmark name.—This is an optional item in L lines. It should be used only when it will make the route easier to understand. It should not be used in place of a position.
6.	Estimated Time of Arrival (ETA).—This is required in any L line where the vessel intends to lay over at the position given in the same L line.	   
Note 5.—Vessels use the following codes to indicate the medical capability on board the vessel:
1.	NONE (no medically trained person onboard).
2.	NURSE (if a trained nurse is onboard).
3.	PA (if a physician's assistant or paramedic is onboard).
4.	MD (if a medical doctor or physician is onboard).	 
